<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Frogs | Yorick Lambreghts</title>
    <link>https://yoricklambreghts.com/tags/frogs/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://yoricklambreghts.com/tags/frogs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Frogs</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://yoricklambreghts.com/media/icon_hu10960734438886622341.png</url>
      <title>Frogs</title>
      <link>https://yoricklambreghts.com/tags/frogs/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hotspot shelters stimulate frog resistance to chytridiomycosis</title>
      <link>https://yoricklambreghts.com/publication/waddle2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yoricklambreghts.com/publication/waddle2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify&#34;&gt;
Many threats to biodiversity cannot be eliminated; for example, invasive pathogens may be ubiquitous. Chytridiomycosis is a fungal disease that has spread worldwide, driving at least 90 amphibian species to extinction, and severely affecting hundreds of others. Once the disease spreads to a new environment, it is likely to become a permanent part of that ecosystem. To enable coexistence with chytridiomycosis in the field, we devised an intervention that exploits host defences and pathogen vulnerabilities. Here we show that sunlight-heated artificial refugia attract endangered frogs and enable body temperatures high enough to clear infections, and that having recovered in this way, frogs are subsequently resistant to chytridiomycosis even under cool conditions that are optimal for fungal growth. Our results provide a simple, inexpensive and widely applicable strategy to buffer frogs against chytridiomycosis in nature. The refugia are immediately useful for the endangered species we tested and will have broader utility for amphibian species with similar ecologies. Furthermore, our concept could be applied to other wildlife diseases in which differences in host and pathogen physiologies can be exploited. The refugia are made from cheap and readily available materials and therefore could be rapidly adopted by wildlife managers and the public. In summary, habitat protection alone cannot protect species that are affected by invasive diseases, but simple manipulations to microhabitat structure could spell the difference between the extinction and the persistence of endangered amphibians.
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amphibian resistance to chytridiomycosis increases following low-virulence chytrid fungal infection or drug-mediated clearance</title>
      <link>https://yoricklambreghts.com/publication/waddle2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yoricklambreghts.com/publication/waddle2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amphibian biodiversity is experiencing ongoing declines due in part to the infectious disease, chytridiomycosis. Efforts to mitigate the effects of the causal agent of chytridiomycosis, &lt;em&gt;Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt;), in the wild have not been wholly effective. Translocations are an important management tool for amphibians, and immunizations represent a possible strategy for preparing amphibians for release across a landscape where &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We evaluated the utility of using an isolate of &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; that was shown to be hypovirulent to the relict leopard frog Rana onca as a transmissible inoculum for promoting chytridiomycosis resistance. We conducted a co-housing experiment to determine if the isolate we used could be passed between &lt;em&gt;R. onca&lt;/em&gt; without increasing in virulence. We then followed with an experiment where frogs that were exposed to the hypovirulent isolate were then challenged with a virulent &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; isolate. In other experiments, we evaluated whether &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; infections followed by clearance with itraconazole (an antifungal) could increase resistance to chytridiomycosis in &lt;em&gt;R. onca&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rana pipiens&lt;/em&gt; (northern leopard frog).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found that our hypovirulent &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; inoculation was transmissible between hosts, did not cause chytridiomycosis and was effective at imparting long-term chytridiomycosis resistance. &lt;em&gt;Rana onca&lt;/em&gt; inoculated with the hypovirulent &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; isolate had lower pathogen burdens and were 55 times more likely to survive infections by a virulent &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; isolate than non-inoculated frogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For both species, prior exposure to &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; followed by infection clearance with itraconazole resulted in significantly increased survivorship and lower pathogen burdens as compared to controls that had no prior &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; exposure. &lt;em&gt;Rana onca&lt;/em&gt; that were previously exposed to &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; were more than 15 times more likely to survive infections. Previously exposed &lt;em&gt;R. pipiens&lt;/em&gt; survived in higher proportions than controls, but with weaker statistical support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Translocations are an important management tool for many amphibian conservation programs. For amphibian species that have experienced declines due to the disease chytridiomycosis [caused by the pathogen &lt;em&gt;Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt;)], the success of translocations may be limited due to the persistent threat of the disease in the wild. We completed a series of experiments aimed at increasing amphibian resistance to chytridiomycosis using low-virulence, transmissible &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; inoculations and &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; infection followed by clearance with an antifungal (itraconazole). Our low-virulence &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; inoculations were transmissible, did not cause disease and provided long-term resistance against chytridiomycosis. Similarly, infection with &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; and clearance with itraconazole led to increased resistance to chytridiomycosis in subsequent exposures. The use of a low-virulence &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; inoculation could be further developed into a transmissible vaccine, propagating the protective benefits beyond individuals that can be directly inoculated. At this stage, we advise that using the alternative approach of infecting frogs with &lt;em&gt;Bd&lt;/em&gt; from translocation sites followed by clearance of infections with itraconazole may be sensible for increasing host resistance to chytridiomycosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
